Andre (Alice Mary) Norton Papers
Andre (Alice Mary) Norton Papers
1959-1978
Norton, Alice Mary.
16.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, science fiction novelist (pseudonyms Andre Norton, Andrew North, Allen Weston). Collection includes correspondence (1959-1978); typescript drafts, manuscripts, and galley proofs for novels; and published material.
149410
Biographical History
Alice Mary Norton (1912-2005) was an award-winning American science fiction and fantasy author, poet and editor.
Born and educated in Cleveland, Ohio, she began writing and editing at a young age, producing her first novel (which became her second published book) while still in high school. She attended Western Reserve University, although she never graduated due to finances. She worked as assistant librarian and children's librarian at the Cleveland Public Libraries from 1932-1950, working in 38 of their 40 branches, with a brief interruption during World War II to work at the Library of Congress. She left the Cleveland Public Libraries in 1950 to be a reader for Gnome Press, a science fiction publishing house in Hicksville, Long Island, but by 1958 she had published 23 novels and several short stories, and felt confident enough to devote her full time to freelance writing.
Although best known as a science fiction writer under the pseudonym Andre Norton (her other pen name is Andrew North), she has also written mystery, fantasy, historical novels, and westerns. Ms. Norton wrote more than 130 novels, nearly one hundred short stories, and edited numerous anthologies in the science-fiction, fantasy, mystery, and western genres, and her work has been translated into eight languages, including Arabic. She was the first woman to be a Science Fiction Writers of America (SFWA) Grand Master and to be inducted in the Science Fiction and Fantasy Hall of Fame. She received Skylark, Balrog, and World Fantasy awards, and was the first woman to win the Gandalf Grand Master of Fantasy award. She was a member of the Women's National Book Association, Theta Sigma Phi, and encouraged beginning writers with "High Hallack," a retreat and research library for writers which she opened and ran from 1999-2004. The SFWA named an award in her honor, the Andre Norton Award for young adult novels, first given in 2006.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alice Mary Norton Papers consist of two accessions which have not been integrated. There are also a small number of unprocessed additions not reflected in this inventory.
Accession I, acquired in the early 1970s, consists of incoming correspondence, writings, and printed material, including books and fanzines. Inclusive dates of the material are 1962-1969, with bulk dates of 1967-1969. The material is arranged in three groups.
Correspondence consists of incoming letters, arranged alphabetically by surname of correspondent. Within each name, letters are arranged chronologically.
Writings constitute the bulk of the collection and includes manuscripts and printed material, arranged alphabetically by title with all stages of a work arranged together in order of creation. There is generally only one draft of a manuscript, usually a revised typescript. Title entries on the shelf list are the published titles. If the book has not been published, the shelf list title is that of the last draft. Titles of drafts and foreign editions are given if they are different from the main entry. The date given for the manuscript is one of three; in descending order of preferences, it is either 1) composition 2) copyright or 3) publication. The number of folders is indicated by a number in parentheses following the entry.
Published material includes printed copies of Ms. Norton's books, the manuscripts of which are not in the collection, and fanzines subscribed to by Ms. Norton. Books are arranged alphabetically by title with publication information given. Fanzines are arranged alphabetically by title and chronologically within each title.
Accession II, acquired ca. 1978, consists of correspondence, memorabilia, published material, and writings.
Correspondence contains mostly fan mail but also some correspondence from other authors and publishers including John Jakes, Forrest J. Ackerman, Anne McCaffrey, Ursula K. LeGuin, and Isaac Asimov. Memorabilia consists of one book jacket and one business card. Published material contains the galley of a book by Jane Louise Curry and a pamphlet relating to science fiction.
The bulk of this accession is Writings, which contains foreign language editions of several books as well as galleys, proofs, and typescripts for more than 30 of Ms. Norton's books.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence in accession I is separated into general correspondence and correspondence from authors/publishers; within each subseries it is arranged chronologically. Correspondence in accession II is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. In both accessions, Published material and Writings are arranged alphabetically by type and, within that, alphabetically by title.
Related Material
has papers of a number of science fiction authors as well as numerous books, periodicals, fanzines, and other material. For manuscript collections, please see for a complete listing. For additional material, refer to or contact us for further information.
Additional materials and correspondence from Alice Mary Norton can be found in the Arnold Gates Collection of Andre Norton Correspondence.
See also the Gnome Press Records (1948-1952).
Subject and Genre Headings
Women Authors; Science fiction; Literature -- American Fiction; Norton, Alice Mary Archives.; Norton, Andre.; North, Andrew.; Weston, Allen.; Fantasy fiction -- Women authors.; Science fiction -- Women authors.; Fantasy fiction, American.; Science fiction, American.; Women authors, American.; Women novelists, American.; Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alice Mary Norton. Rodney Lesher correspondence, purchased, 2009.
Inventory
- Correspondence (I)
  - Lesher, Rodney, 1963 (Box 16)
  - Ortiz, Ray, 1967 (Box 16)
  - Terry, Patrick A.M., 1967; 1968 (Box 16)
- Writings (I)
  - Books
    - Dark Piper, 1968; ts rev.; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Octagon Magic, 1967; ts rev. (Box 16)
    - Moon of Three Rings
      - Draft, 1966; ts rev.; 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Das Geheimnis der Möndsanger, München, Moewig Verlag, 1969 (Box 16)
    - Operation Time Search, undated; ts rev.; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Sorceress of the Witch World, undated; ts rev.; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Three Against the Witch World, 1962?; ts rev. (Box 17)
    - Uncharted Stars, 1968; ts rev.; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Victory in Janus, undated; ts rev.; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Year of the Unicorn, 1962?; ts rev.; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Warlock of the Witch World, 1967; ts rev.; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - The Zero Stone
      - Draft, 1967; ts. rev; 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Der Schlüssel zur Sternenmacht, München, Moewig Verlag, 1969 (Box 18)
- Published material (I)
  - Books
    - The Beast Master, Harmondsworth, Middlesex, England, Penguin Books Ltd., 1968 (Box 18)
    - Catseye, Harmondsworth, Middlesex, England, Penguin Books Ltd., 1967 (Box 18)
    - Lord of Thunder, Harmondsworth, Middlesex, England, Penguin Books Ltd., 1968 (Box 18)
    - Star Man's Son, London, Victor Gollancz Ltd., 1968 (Box 18)
  - Fanzines
    - Amra, Jan 1961; Vol. II, nos. 14-30, 32-35, 41, 43-45 (Box 19)
    - Anubis, Spring 1967; Vol. I, no. 2 (Box 19)
    - Erb-Dom, Dec 1966; No. 19 (Box 19)
    - The Info Journal, Spring 1967; Vol. I, no. 1 (Box 19)
    - Kallikanzaros, Sep 1967; no. 2 (Box 19)
    - Niekas, Spring 1967; no. 18; folders (Box 19)
    - Psychotic, Jan 1968; no. 23 (Box 19)
    - Riverside Quarterly, May-Jun 1965; Vol I, no. 4 (Box 19)
    - Taft Progress Report, Nov 1966; no. 9 (Box 19)
    - Yandro, Jan 1968; Vol. XVI, no. 1; folders (Box 19)
- Correspondence (II)
  - General
    - 1959 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1970, 18 folders (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971, 16 folders (Box 2)
    - 1971-1974, 16 folders (Box 3)
    - 1974-1975, 14 folders (Box 4)
    - 1975-1976, 15 folders (Box 5)
    - 1976-1977, 15 folders (Box 6)
    - 1977-1978, 15 folders (Box 7)
    - 1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Other authors and publishers
    - 1966-1970, 7 folders (Box 8)
- Memorabilia (II)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
- Published material (II)
  - Galley, The Magical Cupboard (Box 8)
  - Pamphlet, The Dipple Chronicle (Box 8)
- Writings (II)
  - Books
    - Blut der Sternengotter (Box 8)
    - Der Schlusel zur Sternenmacht (Box 8)
    - Der Unheimliche Planet (Box 8)
    - Die Eiskrone (Box 8)
    - Riscatto Comica (Box 8)
    - Sterne ohne Namen (Box 8)
    - Verfemte des Alls (Box 8)
  - Galleys
    - Breed to Come (Box 9)
    - The Crystal Gryphon (Box 9)
    - Forerunner Foray (Box 9)
    - Here Abide Monsters, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Iron Cage, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - The Jargoon Pard (Box 9)
    - Knave of Dreams, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Lavender-Green Magic, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - No Night Without Stars, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - The Opal-Eyed Fan (Box 9)
    - Quag Keep, 5 folders (Box 10)
    - Red Hart Magic, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Tomorrow (Box 10)
    - Velvet Shadows (Box 10)
    - The White Jade Fox (Box 10)
    - The Wraiths of Time, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Proofs
    - Fear Sword, Fear Spell (Box 10)
    - Mousetrap (Box 10)
    - Quag Keep, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Red Hart Magic (Box 10)
  - Typescripts
    - Android-at-Arms (Box 11)
    - Breed to Come (Box 11)
    - By a Hair (Box 11)
    - The Crystal Gryphon (Box 11)
    - Death Collects a Manuscript, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Dragon Magic (Box 11)
    - Dread Companion (Box 11)
    - Exiles of the Stars, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Fireside Book of Ghost Stories (Box 11)
    - Here Abide Monsters (Box 11)
    - High Sorcery (Box 11)
    - The House that Once Was (Box 11)
    - Ice Crown (Box 11)
    - Iron Cage, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - The Jargoon Pard (Box 11, 12)
    - Knave of Dreams, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - Landing on Zimmorah (Box 12)
    - Lavender-Green Magic (Box 12)
    - Merlin's Mirror, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Nightmare (Box 12)
    - No Night Without Stars, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - The Opal-Eyed Fan, 2 folders (Box 12, 13)
    - Outside (Box 13)
    - Postmarked the Stars (Box 13)
    - Quag Keep, 7 folders (Box 13)
    - Red Hart Magic, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Red Velvet, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Ship of Mist (Box 13)
    - Small Shadows Creep (Box 13)
    - Spell of the Witch World (Box 13)
    - Star Ka'at (Box 13)
    - Star Ka'at Sequel (Box 13)
    - Star Ka'at World or Star Ka'at Kin (Box 13)
    - Sword of Lost Battles (Box 13)
    - Sword of Shadow (Box 13)
    - Tales to be Told (Box 13)
    - Through the Needle's Eye (Box 13)
    - Toys of Tamison (Box 14)
    - Ully the Piper (Box 14)
    - Untitled, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Velvet, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - We're not a Family (Box 14)
    - The White Jade Fox, 6 folders (Box 14)
    - The Willing Givers (Box 14)
    - Wraiths of Time, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Youthful Inexperience (Box 14)
    - Yurth Burden, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Zarsthor's Bane, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Unbound books
    - Octagon Magic (Box 15)